Guide to the William Styron Papers, 1855-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Printed Material Series, 1900-1998 and undated
  - Clippings Group
    - Lie Down in Darkness, (2 folders) (Box PM 17)
    - The Long March
    - Set This House on Fire, (2 folders)
    - Sophie's Choice, (5 folders)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials
    - 1942-1997, undated, (5 folders) (Box PM 18)
- Audiovisual Material Series, 1963-1996 and undated
  The Audiovisual Material series includes audiotapes, videotapes, and photographs. Videotapes include the finished production of Dr. Joel Foreman's 1982 documentary on Styron, "William Styron: A Portrait" and 37 videotapes representing all the footage shot in the making of the documentary. Use copies are available for "William Styron: A Portrait" and all 37 production videotapes. Several other videotaped documentaries about Styron are also included. Interviews with Styron are represented among both the audiotapes and videotapes. Audiocassettes also include a 20-cassette reading of Sophie's Choice, by Wolfram Kandinsky; addresses by Styron; and conferences with Styron and Ossie Davis, and James Baldwin on Confessions of Nat Turner, and with Styron and Thérèse de St. Phalle in Russia. Photographs include images of the Styron family, of Styron at ceremonies and speaking engagements, of the filming of "Sophie's Choice," and of Christchurch School. Use copies of videotapes and reel-to-reel tapes must be made before use.
  - Videocassettes Group
    - Videotape 1 (Box AV 1)
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with Vera Elsinboss, Styron friend and pharmacist (on cassette: 'Test tape - Canfield's pharmacy') 1982, Apr. 27
    - Videotape 2
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with Bob Munson, Roxbury marketer (on cassette: 'Munsun's store') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 3
      Foreman Videotape: Interior shots of Munson food market; Exterior shots of Styron property on Racum Road (on cassette: 'Munson's cutaways; outside cutaways - Styron's house') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 4
      Foreman Videotape: Styron driving through Roxbury with monologue on his residency (on cassette 'Styron's house; Ride to Munson's with W. S.') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 5
      Foreman Videotape: Rose and Bill Styron cooking and planning a dinner party; Styron soaks Virginia ham and talks about his heritage; Styron playing with his dogs (on cassette: 'Styron's house; Kitchen sequence; 1:30') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 6
      Foreman Videotape: Styron walks through Revolutionary War graveyard and talks; His reflections on death (on cassette: 'Ham cutaways; Dogs outside') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 7 (Box AV 2)
      Foreman Videotape: Styron completing his daily walk; Scenes from rural Roxbury (on cassette: 'Part II graveyard walk; 1st. take on pond/boat at end of tape') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 8
      Foreman Videotape: Styron reads selected passages from his work (on cassette: 'begin tape/pond/boat; end pond/boat') 1982, Apr. 28
    - Videotape 9
      Foreman Videotape: Styron reads selected passages from his work (on cassette: 'Rose interview') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 10
      Foreman Videotape:Interview with Rose Styron, 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 11
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with Rose Styron, 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 12
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with Rose Styron (on cassette: End Rose Styron/ Poem) 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 13 (Box AV 3)
      Foreman Videotape: Styron walks through Canfield Pharmacy and chats with Vera Elsinboss; Styron scrubs and cuts hock from Virginia ham, 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 14
      Foreman Videotape: Styron boils ham; images from the Styron kitchen; Styron enacts his daily writing modus operandi (on cassette: 'Styron at his bar/desk') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 15
      Foreman Videotape: Styron writing; shots of Styron living room (on cassette: 'Inside and outside of Styron house') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videtape 16
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with Styron (on cassette: 'Beauty shots bar room; Styron dining room interview') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 17
      Foreman Videotape: Styron skins and slathers ham; additional shots of Styron writing as sun sets (on cassette: 'Ham glaze') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 18
      Foreman Videotape: Styron reads and comments upon letters to his father (on cassette: 'Styron interview') 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 19 (Box AV 4)
      Foreman Videotape: Styron interview, 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 20
    - Videotape 21
    - Videotape 22
    - Videotape 23
      Foreman Videotape: Styron reads from works, 1982, Apr. 29
    - Videotape 24
      Foreman Videotape: Styron drives through Roxbury / monologue on same (on cassette: hand cutaways / Bill driving) 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 25 (Box AV 5)
      Foreman Videotape: Same as # 24; shots of Roxbury; shots of Munson's farm (on cassette: Sheep farm) 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 26
      Foreman Videotape: Styron walking on Roxbury backroads, no commentary, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 27
      Foreman Videotape: Shots of items in Styron parlor; shots of dinner, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 28
      Foreman Videotape: Styron cuts ham and talks about heritage; opening shots of Styron party 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 29
      Foreman Videotape: Shots of Styron and guests in living room; interview with John Marquand, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 30
      Foreman Videotape: Styron's dinner party, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 31 (Box AV 6)
      Foreman Videotape: Shots of Styron dinner in dining room, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 32
      Foreman Videotape: Dinner in dining room; interview with Arthur Miller, 1982, Apr. 30
      DVD Duplicating Master.
    - Videotape 33
      Foreman Videotape: Dessert and conversation, 1982, Apr. 30
    - Videotape 34
      Foreman Videotape: Interview with John Marquand (on cassette: John Phillips interview; Roxbury cutaways) 1982, Apr. 30- May 1
    - Videotape 35
      Foreman Videotape: Interior and exterior shots of Canfield Pharmacy; exterior shots of Styron house, 1982, May1
    - Videotape 36
      Foreman Videotape: Styron interview, 1982, May1
    - Videotape 37 (Box AV 7)
      Foreman Videotape: Styron interview (Roxbury cuts), 1982, May1
    - Videotape 38, (tape damaged)
      Foreman Videotape: "William Styron: A Portrait," produced by Joel Foreman, 1982(Master Copy, "Second generation," 58:35)
    - Videotape 39
      "Foreman Videotape: William Styron: A Portrait," produced by Joel Foreman, 1982(Use Copy, "Third generation," 58:35)
    - Videotape 40
      "William Styron," CBS Cable Signature, 1981, Dec. 14(Beta II Master Copy, Approx. 20:00)
    - Videotape 41
      "William Styron," CBS Cable Signature, 1981, Dec. 14(VHS Use Copy, Approx. 20:00)
    - Videotape 42
      "First Edition: William Styron," PBS interview,1986
    - Videotape 43
      "The Vineyard Voice," Interview with Styron, Producer and Host William Marks, MA,1989,Summer
  - Audiocassettes Group--Mastercopies
    Mastercopies: not for research use. Tape numbers correspond to those of use tapes in boxes AV 10 and AV 11.
    - Tapes 1-5 (Box AV 8)
      Audio tapes of interviews of Styron by Dr. Robert K. Morris (5 cassettes)
    - Tape 6
      Conversation between Thérèse de St. Phalle and Styron, re: conference in Russia [ca. 1969] (1 tape)
    - Tape 7
      "Gray Matters: Depression and the Brain and A Conversation with Mike Wallace, Art Buchwald, and William Styron, The Dana Alliance for Brain Initiatives, 1996" (1 tape) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tape 8
      Duke University Club, 1992, Oct. 27(1 tape)
    - Tape 9
      An unrehearsed interview with William Styron for the Robert Penn Warren Oral History Project. Interview conducted by Susan Allen in Roxbury, CT, 1980, May 5(1 tape)
    - Tapes 10-19
      Sophie's Choice read by Wolfram Kandinsky, part I, produced by Books on Tape, Inc.,1984 (10 tapes) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tapes 20-29
      Sophie's Choice read by Wolfram Kandinsky, part II, produced by Books on Tape, Inc.,1984 (10 tapes) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tape 30
      Audio tape of interview of Styron by Paul Baily for broadcast by BBC, August 2,1982 (1 tape)
    - Tapes 31-33 (Box AV 9)
      See box AV 15
    - Tapes 34-35
    - Tapes 36-37
    - Tape 38
      Audio tape of talk given by Styron at City Arts of San Francisco (1 tape) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tape 39
      Chicago anti-Semite (1-tape)
    - Tape 40
      Ossie Davis, William Styron and James Baldwin on Confessions of Nat Turner, 1968, May(1 tape)
    - Tape 41
      Ossie Davis and William Styron on telephone re: Confessions of Nat Turner from "Mike Wallace at Large," 1968, Aug. 1(1 tape)
  - Audiocassettes Group--Use Copies
    - Tapes 1-5 (Box AV 10)
    - Tape 6
    - Tape 7
      "Gray Matters: Depression and the Brain and A Conversation with Mike Wallace, Art Buchwald, and William Styron, The Dana Alliance for Brain Initiatives,1996" (1 tape) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tape 8
    - Tape 9
    - Tapes 10-19
      Sophie's Choice read by Wolfram Kandinsky, part I, produced by Books on Tape, Inc.,1984(10 tapes) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tapes 20-29
      Sophie's Choice read by Wolfram Kandinsky, part II, produced by Books on Tape, Inc.,1984(10 tapes) accompanying information in box AV 12
    - Tape 30
      Audio tape of interview of Styron by Paul Baily for broadcast by BBC, August 2,1982(1 tape)
    - Tapes 31-33 (Box AV 11)
    - Tapes 34-35
    - Tapes 36-37
    - Tape 38
    - Tape 39
    - Tape 40
    - Tape 41
  - Transcripts and Material Accompanying Audiocassettes
    Restricted Transcripts are housed in Box AV 15
    - 1984 - Copyright information regarding Sophie's Choice ("Books on Tape" version, tapes #10-29 in this collection) (Box AV 12)
    - 1994 - Flyer and station list accompanying address by Styron for City Arts of San Francisco (Tape #38 in this collection)
    - 1996 - Transcript and brochure: "Grey Matters: A Conversation with Art Buchwald, William Styron, and Mike Wallace" (Tape #7 in this collection)
  - Miscellaneous Formats Group
    - Reel to reel audio tape of Styron and Ossie Davis from "Wallace at Large," 1968, Aug.1 (Box AV 13)
    - Styron reading from Lie Down in Darkness,1963, Calliope Records (7 inch long play record, 2 copies)
    - Reel to reel audio tape of panel discussion with Styron on Confessions of Nat Turner, 1969, June, Harford, CT.
    - Reel to reel audio tape of Styron on Confessions of Nat Turner programmed for "Literature at Large," 1967, Nov. 29,recorded at Wilberforce University, OH.
    - Reel to reel audio tape of Ossie Davis, James Baldwin and Styron on Confessions of Nat Turner, 1968, May,at Eugene's, Beverly Hills
  - Photographs Group (Box AV 14)
    Photographs.
  - Restricted Audiovisual Materials
    - Tapes 31-33 (Box AV 15)
      Audio tapes of interview of Styron by James L. W. West III on Thanksgiving1986,Styron's home, Roxbury (3 tapes) restricted
    - Tapes 34-35
      Audio tapes of interview of Styron by James L. W. West III on August 12,1987at Vineyard Haven (2 tapes) restricted
    - Tapes 36-37
      Audio tapes of interview of Styron by James L. W. West III on December 1,1987in Roxbury, CT (2 tapes) restricted
    - Transcripts of the above interviews -- Restricted, (3 folders)
- Scrapbooks, ca. 1925-1968
  Scrapbooks assembled by Styron's father documenting his son's life and later literary career. Scrapbook 1 begins with childhood photographs, artwork, and an analysis of young Styron's handwriting. The remainder of this volume and the 2 later volumes are filled primarily with reviews and publicity generated by Styron's first three novels, interspersed with occasional letters and photographs.
  - Scrapbook 1 ca. 1925-1968(restoration) (Box SB 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, ca. 1939-1967 (Box SB 2)
  - Scrapbook 3, ca. 1959-1965 (Box SB 3)
  - Fragile - Original of scrapbook 1 (Box SB 4)
- Miscellaneous Material Series, 1855-1991 and undated
  Miscellaneous papers include literary awards and medals and accompanying documentation, genealogical information, an autograph/commonplace album of Catherine Clark (Styron's great-aunt), honorary degrees awarded to Styron, a guestbook (1979), and legal papers pertaining to the publication of Styron's works.
  - Awards and medals, 1970-1989, (8 items) (Box M 1)
  - Catherine Clark's Album, 1855-1859 (Box M 2)
  - Guestbook from party celebrating Styron's 54th birthday and the publication of Sophie's Choice, 1979
  - Genealogical information (undated)
  - Legal papers pertaining to Lie Down in Darkness, 1959-1964
  - Legal papers pertaining to Set This House on Fire, 1961-1962
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1951-1980 and undated
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1951-1991 and undated
- Oversize Material, 1967-1993
  - Serials (Box OS 1)
    - 1967, Oct. 15-31 - La Quinzaine Littéraire "Styron et les Noirs," (p. 12)
    - 1979, July 30- Variety Advertisement for Sophie's Choice
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material
  - 1982 - Poster for "Sophie's Choice" (film)
  - 1993 - "Vanishing South" Calendar, featuring art of Hubert Shuptrine with commentary by Styron
  - 1979 - Book-of-the-Month Club advertisement for Sophie's Choice
  - Clippings
    - 1967-1989, (2 folders)
  - Promotional poster for Sophie's Choice, English ed., circa 1980 (Box OS 2)
  - Commandeur de l'ordre des Arts et des Lettres: Award certificate and related correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box OS 2)
  - Primo Levi clipping and related memo, 1988 (Box OS 2)
  - Chance in a million, facsimilie keepsake proof, 1993
  - Darkness Visible poster, mounted on foam board, undated (Box OS 2)
  - The Confessions of Nat Turner poster, undated (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2006-0105), (1 box)
  Unprocessed addition (06-105) (.4 lin. ft) contains Styron's copy of The Confessions of Nat Turner and a binder of letters from Styron to Bertha Krantz, Robert D. Loomis, and others, 1967-1993.
  - Styron memorial service materials (Folder 1)
- Accession (2007-0145), 2007, (1 folder)
  Unprocessed addition (07-145) (6 items, .1 lin. ft.; dated 2007) contains copies of material from Styron's memorial service, including the program, book of reminiscences, and transcript. This material is boxed in box 1 of 08-142.
  - Styron memorial service materials (Folder 1)
- Accession (2008-0012), 1943-2006 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Unprocessed accession (0.8 lin. ft.; 600 items) which includes Styron's leather portfolio, handwritten drafts of his writings, typescripts, essays, speeches, and some correspondence from his to his father (dated 1943-1952). Also includes correspondence from his wife, Rose, around the time of his death in 2006, and a copy of the New York Times obituary. Also includes a leather portfolio with drafts of his work, photographs, clippings, and a photograph album from his daughter's film, Shadrach.
  - William Styron leather portfolio with drafts (Box 1 (Acc. 08/012))
  - Drafts and essays (3 folders)
  - Literary portraits (published and drafts)
  - Speeches and writings
  - Letters to his father, 1943-1952
  - Published articles and essays, some drafts
  - Drafts and published short stories, including the following: (Box 2 (Acc. 08/012))
    - Essays on Sophie's Choice
    - Lie Down in Darkness
    - F. Scott Fitzgerald
  - Drafts, essays, and short stories relating to war (5 folders)
  - Correspondence from Rose, 2006
  - Photographs, clippings, photograph album, 1992-1998 and undated
  - William Styron interview transcripts, 2006
  - Obituary, 2006
- Accession (2008-0072), 1990-2003 and undated, (1 box)
  Unprocessed addition (08-072) (180 items, .6 lin. ft.; dated 1990-2003 and undated) comprises mainly letters to Styron regarding his works, especially DARKNESS VISIBLE. Also includes letters regarding appearances requested or planned.
  - (Box 1 (Acc. 08/072))
- Accession (2008-0142), 1966-2003 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Unprocessed addition (08-142) (388 items, .8 lin. ft; dated 1966-2007 and undated) mainly comprises incoming correspondence, which occasionally contains clippings, photographs, and other incidental materials. In addition, includes original manuscripts for several short works by the author, many annotated, as well as some handwritten manuscript pages for SOPHIE'S CHOICE. There are also two dvds of Styron's memorial service. Box 1 of this material includes Acc. 07-145.
  - (Box 1 (Acc. 08/142))
  - Correspondence, 1979-1991 and undated (9 folders)
  - Acc. 07-145 Memorial service program, reminiscences, and transcript
  - Memorial Service dvds
  - Manuscript originals: Sophie's Choice, Cannes Film Festival notes, "Shabaka", Virginia Foster Durr, Caleb
  - (Box 2 (Acc. 08/142))
  - Manuscript originals (5 folders): Yet alone shall I prevail, Saipan: July 1945, The way of the warrior
- Accession (2008-0294), (1 box)
  Unprocessed addition (0.4 lin. ft.; 300 items) collected by James L.W. West III, a literature professor at Pennsylvania State University. A portion of this accession remains on deposit. Included are original and digitally scanned manuscripts, drafts, essays, short stories, and speeches. This accession is included in Box 2 (Acc. 08/012).
  - James West III addition (6 folders) (Box 2 (Acc. 08/012))
- Accession (2011-0142), (1 box)
  Addition (11-142) (0.6 lin. ft.; 500 items) was donated by Styron's editor, Robert Loomis. It includes drafts and clippings, as well as photographs used in Styron publications.
  - Yet Alone Shall I Prevail draft, undated (Box 1)
  - A Tidewater Morning drafts, 1993
  - The Way of the Warrior draft, 1985 and undated
  - Various essays, undated
  - Clippings about Styron, 1985-1986
  - Photographs from publications
- Accession (2012-0017), (1 box)
  - Cimarron Review 12 (July 1970), and note from William Swanson to Styron, 9 Oct. 1970 (Box 1)
    Issue includes "Religious Implications in The Confessions of Nat Turner" by Swanson (pp. 57-66)
  - Michael Stephens, Circles End, 1982, and note from Stephens to Styron, 28 Feb. 1982 (Box 1)
  - Carlos Fuentes, Aura, 1986 (Box 1)
    Inscribed to Styron; has Rose Styron's ownership signature
  - Hiber Conteris, Ten Percent of Life, uncorrected proof (1987), with note from Conteris to Styron, 26 July 1987 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Architectural Digest associate editor Adele Cygelman to Styron, 30 July 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ron Schick and Julia van Haaften, The View from Space: American Astronaut Photography, 1962-1972 (1988), with foreword by Styron (Box 1)
  - Neil Casey, ed., Unholy Ghost: Writers on Depression, 2002 (Box 1)
    Has Rose Styron's ownership signature, as well as her underlinings/notations (relevant to Styron) throughout introduction
- Accession (2012-0131), (2 boxes)
  Proofs and galleys related to In the Clap Shack; manuscript fragments of The Way of the Warrior and a few essays; and a research and clippings file on Nat Turner.
  - Proofs of In the Clap Shack, undated (Box 1)
  - Proofs of In the Clap Shack, 1973 (Box 1)
    Master set, first pass
  - Proofs of In the Clap Shack, undated (Box 1)
    Master set, second pass
  - Foul matter, In the Clap Shack, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript fragments, The Way of the Warrior, undated (Box 1)
  - Essay manuscript fragments, undated (Box 1)
  - Research and clippings, The Confessions of Nat Turner, 1967-1971 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    Clipped reviews and articles about Styron's novel (some covering the backlash against it) and the film adaptation, as well as correspondence, notes, and research documents.
  - Manuscript fragments, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Typed manuscript, The Way of the Warrior, undated (Box 2)
  - Extra copy of onion paper copy, undated (Box 2)
- Accession (2013-0017), (1 box)
  Original blocks used to create advertisements for William Styron's novel The Confessions of Nat Turner.
  - Set of two printing blocks (Box 1)